本字幕僅用於學習交流，禁止一切商業用途
導演      編劇
亞歷桑德羅·佐杜洛夫斯基
現實之舞
金錢如同血液
Money is like blood,
流動之時賦予生命
it gives life if it flows.
金錢如同基督
Money is like Christ,
分享之時受到祝福
it blesses you if you share it.
金錢如同佛陀
Money is like Buddha,
你若不行履
if you don't work,
就無法懂得
you don't get it.
金錢啟示那些使用它的
Money enlightens those who use it
以開啟世界之花
to open the flower of the world,
詛咒那些膜拜它的人
and damns those who glorify it,
混淆富足與靈魂
confounding riches with the soul.
毫無差異
There is no difference
金錢與意識毫無差異
between money and conscience.
意識與死亡毫無差異
There is no difference
between conscience and death.
死亡與財富毫無差異
There is no difference
between death and wealth.
你這混帳為何總這麼羞怯？
Why the hell are you so shy?
感知那個孩子吧，困陷於你胸口的孩子，
Feeling the child
trapped within your breast,
眼中滿是永恒的迷失.
the eyes full of an eternal absence.
一直是局外人，永恒的局外人.
Always outsiders, eternal outsiders.
叫了你你就跟過來！
Come when you're told!
你好啊傑！
Hello Jaime!
好久不見啦！
It's been ages!
商鋪經營得順利麽？
Everything alright in the shop?
你那宏偉的烏克蘭小屋！
The Gran Casa Ukrania!
你想念我們了麽？
Do you miss us?
我猜你想了！
I bet you do!
你依舊那樣強壯麽？
Are you still just as strong?
你覺得呢？
What do you think?
你兒子知不知道你曾是這裏的攀繩高手？
Does your son know
you used to climb ropes here?
你現在還能行麽？
Can you still do it?
當然行！
Of course I can!
讓我們看看，眼見才為實.
Let us see, as the blind say.
-走！看看去！
-閉嘴，你這死胖子！
- Let us go!
- Shut up, you old fatso!
現實，現實之舞！
Reality, the dance of reality!
讓我們看看你能做些什麽！
Let us see what you can do!
爬呀！向上！
UP you go!
我能行！
I can do it!
你依舊保持著你那迷人的肌肉！
You still have your lovely muscles!
但你强力的拳頭，我懷疑它！
But your mighty fists, I doubt it!
記得你向觀眾挑戰拳擊麽？
Remember you challenged
the audience to box you?
我當然記得！
Of course I do!
打倒他，他們就能得到賞金.
They got cash
if they beat him.
是的，但兩擊之內，他就能將他們放倒在地.
Yes, but with two blows
he would lay them flat on the floor.
如今你在銷售熱褲，
Now that you sell knickers,
你還能做到麼？
can you still do it?
當然可以.
Of course I can.
那我們套上拳套.
Let us put on the gloves.
拳套？
Gloves?
赤手空拳幹吧，像男人一樣！
Bare fists, like men!
別這樣爸爸，他們會殺了你的.
Don't,Papa. They'll kill you.
閉嘴，你這懦夫！他們會說我兒子是個娘娘腔.
Shut up, you coward!
They'll say my son is a queer.
小心點！我們會吃了你！
Watch out!
We're going to eat you!
天呐，眞是噩夢！
Oh, horror!
傑打了我！
Jaime hit me!
我要昏倒了.
I'm going to faint.
胡蘿蔔，胡蘿蔔！
Carrot!
-我好害怕！
-害怕？
- I'm scared!
- Scared?
-永遠不准你這麼說！
-他在害怕！
- Don't ever say that!
- He's scared!
托科皮亞，在這里顫抖，
Tocopilla, this tremor,
這里岩石的味道，
this scent of stones,
這個小鎮的挽歌
this lament of a small town
被陽光撕裂成碎片，
torn to shreds by the sun,
那些患病的街道
those patient streets
渴望著哪怕一顆水滴.
longing for a drop of water.
烏克蘭小屋！
Casa Ukrania!
歡迎光臨烏克蘭小屋！
Welcome to Casa Ukrania!
進來快進來！
Come on in!
亞歷桑德羅！
Alejandrito!
為什麽要跑掉，我的父親？
Why are you running, my dear father?
我不是妳的父親！我是你兒子！
I'm not your father! I'm your son!
亞歷桑德羅！
Alejandrito!
瘋吧！
Get mad!
我不是同性戀！
I am not a faggot!
你嚇不到我！
You don't scare me!
隨你變得多麼龐大！
Get as big as you want!
夠了夠了，傻孩子！
That's enough, silly child!
-放開我，你這老酒鬼！
-夠了！
- Let me go, you old drunk!
- Enough!
一個小小的石子就足以殺死
A single stone can kill
大海中所有的游鱼.
all the fish in the sea.
我，聖杯的女皇，如是說.
So say I, the Queen of Cups.
放開我！
Let me go!
快逃吧！
Run!
你這個小兇手！
You murdering child!
你折磨大海，它們都被你殺光了！
By torturing the sea you killed them all!
不是的！
No!
快滾開,你這個老巫婆！
Get lost, you old hag!
我感到困惑.
I felt confused:
我是應該承受這些沙丁魚的痛苦？
should I suffer the anguish
of the sardines
還是應該為海鷗的愉悅而感到欣喜？
or should I delight
in the joy of the gulls.
當我看到海鷗掠奪著它們的盛宴，
The balance tipped
in favour of anguish
平衡傾斜了，偏向于痛苦的一方.
when I saw the seagulls
deprived of their banquet.
在那個世界，那個讓我覺得自己像個陌生人的世界,
In that world,
in which I felt a stranger,
一切事物都緊密相聯，
all things were connected
聯繫在苦難與歡愉交織的網絡之中.
in a web of suffering
and pleasure.
冰淇淋！肉桂和香草口味的冰淇淋！
Ice cream! Cinnamon and vanilla!
華爾街的崩潰
The collapse of Wall Street
使70%的智利人陷入貧窮.
has impoverished 70% of the Chileans.
我們的總統，上校卡洛斯·伊瓦涅斯·德爾坎波
Our president, Colonel Carlos Ibáñez del Campo
宣佈國家公庫
declares that the Public Treasury
正處於空前難遇的發展基點.
has never been on a better footing.
不久，會為所有民眾提供就業崗位.
Soon there will be employment for all.
你們這些撒謊的暴發戶！
You lying jumped-up private!
行行好，年輕人，我只是想在這裡撓撓背可以麼？
If you allow me, young man,
I'll just scratch my back.
願意讓我幫你撓嗎？
Would you like me to do it for you?
好啊，如果我沒惹你反感.
Well, if I don't disgust you.
吃掉我的冰淇淋吧，如果我也沒惹你反感的話~
Finish my ice cream,
if I don't disgust you either!
別這麼說！我很高興~
Come on! It would be a pleasure.
弄疼你了嗎？
Am I hurting you?
自從我因礦難失去了手臂
Since I lost my hands in the mine
美國佬就把我趕了出去，再沒有人碰過我.
and the Yanks kicked me out,
no one has touched me.
可憐人.
Poor man.
你這個骯髒的廢人，
You dirty cripple,
過來，你該被關進監獄！
come back, and you'll go to jail!
爸爸，是我要求給他撓背的.
I offered to scratch his back.
-他自己做不到！
-給我閉嘴！
- He can't do it!
- Shut up!
別讓這種穢物靠近你！
Don't let this filth come near you!
他們滿身都是虱子！
They're full of lice!
為什麼你做派像斯大林一樣？
Why dress up like Stalin?
明明說自己是共產主義者，卻只尊重金錢.
You say you're a communist
but you only respect the rich.
要是我有錢，你肯定會親吻我的殘肢！
If I had money, you'd kiss my stumps!
操蛋的猶太人！婊子養的！
You fucking Jew! Son of a bitch!
滾遠點！
Fuck off!
要是敢再來，我打斷你的狗腿！
If you come back, I'll cut your legs off!
-你這王八蛋！
傑，讓他走吧！
- Motherfucker!
- Jaime, let him go!
幹嘛要安撫那個廢人？
Why hug that cripple?
你喜歡男人，是嗎！？
You like men, do you?
就憑這一頭娘娘腔的鬃毛，
With that girlish mane,
我們對你還能有什麼指望？
what else could we expect?
這頭髮讓他看上去像個同性戀！
With that hair, he looks like a faggot!
對他放尊重些，
Show him some respect,
亞歷桑德羅是聖潔的.
Alejandro is holy.
聖潔，真是一派胡言！
Holy, my bollocks!
告訴他你為什麼叫他父親而不是兒子！
Tell him why you call him your father
and not your son.
現在就告訴他！
Tell him now!
在俄羅斯，
In Russia,
我的母親墜入了愛河，
my mother fell in love
愛上了我的父親，
with my father,
一位英俊的俄羅斯舞者.
a handsome Russian dancer.
為了逃離
They were on the run
憎恨猶太民族的哥薩克人.
from the Jew-hating Cossacks.
我父母移居到了阿根廷，
They emigrated to Argentina
在那裡他們辛勤地耕作
where they worked hard to cultivate
屬於自己的一小塊土地.
a small piece of land.
為點燃一盞油燈，我的父親
To light a lamp, my father
攀上了一個
climbed on to a cask
盛滿酒精的木桶.
of alcohol.
桶蓋在他體重的壓迫下碎裂了.
The lid broke under his weight.
他被活生生燒死在那裡.
He was burned alive.
當我懷上了身孕，
When I got pregnant,
我知道你就是
I knew you would be
我父親的輪迴轉世.
my father reincarnated.
就這樣，
And so it was,
你誕生了，有著同樣厚實的金髮.
you were born with the same thick blond hair.
這把梳子
This comb
是唯一一件我父親的遺物.
is the only thing that remains of my father.
夠了！
Enough!
唬人的童話！
Fairy tales!
兒子就是兒子！
Your son is your son!
你這些無理取鬧會把他搞瘋的！
You'll drive him crazy with this nonsense!
不要帶走他！他是我的！
Don't take him away! He's mine!
你敢！
Just try it!
向我道歉.
Apologise!
對不起.
Sorry.
烏克蘭小屋！烏克蘭小屋！
Casa Ukrania!
做掉高價！
Down with high prices!
你來啦，操蛋的猶太人！
There you are, fucking Jew!
我告訴過你別再來的！
I told you not to come back!
求你別這樣，爸爸！
Please don't, Papa!
放手！
Let go!
就是那個猶太人打了我！
That's the Jew who hit me!
過來你這個混球！老屁眼！
C'mon you jerk! Asshole!
蟑螂！蟑螂！烹調蟑螂！
Cockroach! Cooking cockroach!
墓穴！墓碑！葬在墓內！
The tomb and the tombstone!
Entombed in the tomb!
炸藥！欠操的肥婊子！
The dynamite! Fucking fat bitch!
什麼都沒給我們！還把我們炸碎！
Blows us apart! Gives us but nothing!
蟑螂！蟑螂！烹調蟑螂了！
Cockroach! Cooking cockroach!
墓穴！墓碑！葬在墓內啊！
The tomb and the tombstone!
Entombed in the tomb!
炸藥！欠操的肥婊子！
The dynamite! Fucking fat bitch!
什麼都沒予我們！還把我們炸碎！
Blows us apart!
Gives us but nothing!
他們砍掉了我們的腿，
They cut off our legs,
他們砍掉了我們的臂！
They cut off our arms!
炸藥沒有心靈，
Dynamite has no heart,
它輕輕地將我們撕爛,
It strokes us apart.
炸藥沒有心靈.
Dynamite has no heart,
它輕輕地將我們扯爛,
It strokes us apart.
傻逼！婊子養的！
Fucking jerk! Son of a bitch!
為什麼你是這樣一個懦夫！？
How can you be such a coward?
不許亂動！
Keep still!
媽媽會生氣的！
My mother will be angry!
你外表像一個娼婦，而不是一個男人.
You look like a whore, not like a man.
安份點，否則我把你的頭髮扯下來！
Calm down or I'll tear your hair out!
開始吧.
Go ahead.
-怎麼了，小矮子？
-很疼.
- What's the matter, midget?
- It really hurts.
別為不屬於自己的東西感到痛苦.
Don't suffer for what isn't yours.
這是你祖父的頭髮.
It's your grandfather's hair.
這妄想該結束了！
Enough of this delusion!
我們走.
Let's go!
你可以開始學學如何做一個男人了！
Now you'll learn how to be a man!
你兒子回來了！
Here is your son!
你金色的捲髮呢？
Your golden curls?
你是誰？
Who are you?
我不認識你.
I don't know you.
叛徒！
Traitor!
永遠別再碰我！
Don't ever touch me again.
我叫你走開！
I'm telling you to go.
你和傑...
You and Jaime...
殺害了我的父親！
have murdered my father.
你離我而去
You've left me...
讓我成了孤兒.
an orphan.
顧客登門她就會出來的.
She'll come out for the customers.
高價消費去死吧！
Death to high prices!
嘗嘗這個！還有這個！
Take that! And that!
不准動.
Stay still.
男人懂得自我控制！
A man controls himself!
我撓你的腳心.
I'm going to tickle you.
你要是不笑，才配做我的兒子.
If you don't laugh,
you deserve to be my son.
不准笑！
Don't laugh!
很好.
Good.
腋窩.
The armpits!
不准屈服！
Don't give in!
接下來是脖頸.
Now the neck!
堅持住.
Resist!
鼻子.
The nose!
好吧.
Alright.
你開始贏得我的欽佩了.
You're starting to deserve my admiration.
別高興太早，
Don't look so happy,
我只是說“開始”.
I only said "starting to".
如果想我為你驕傲，
If you want me to be proud of you,
必須向我展示，你可以承受住痛苦.
you must show me you can deal with pain.
接下來我要扇你耳光.
I'm going to slap you.
聽你要求，我會加大力度.
If you ask me to, I'll slap you harder.
你越是要我扇，
And the more you ask,
我就扇得越重.
the harder I'll slap.
我們看看你能應付多久.
We'll see how much you can cope with.
開始吧.
Let's begin.
重點.
Harder.
再重點.
你打掉了我的牙，
You broke my tooth,
可是如果你愛我，這不算什麼要緊事.
but if you love me, it doesn't matter.
這當然要緊.
Of course it matters.
走，去看牙醫.
To the dentist.
上車，你們這幫懶惰的混球！
Get on, you lazy bastard!
開去垃圾堆！
To the rubbish dump!
炸藥沒有心靈，
Dynamite has no heart,
它輕輕地將我們撕扯爛.
It strokes us apart.
嘴張大，孩子.
Open wide, my boy.
唾液沾到空氣會很疼.
The air on the saliva must hurt a lot.
男人必須勇敢.
A man must be brave.
如果按我說得做，
If you do as I ask
你會贏得我的欽佩.
then you will win my admiration.
治療過程中別讓他涂麻藥.
Let him treat you without anaesthetic.
聽著.
Look.
意志能夠克服疼痛.
Willpower overcomes pain.
讓我們瞧瞧你像不像我.
Let's see if you are like me.
嘴張大，這只是一針止痛劑.
Open wide. It's just a little painkiller.
不必注射，胡里奧先生.
No injection, Don Julio.
他會很疼的.
But it will really hurt.
我給你兩瓶紅酒.
I'll send you two bottles of wine.
你說呢孩子？
What does the boy have to say?
我不需要注射，先生.
I don't need an injection, sir.
好吧，既然你這麼說了.
Well, if you say so.
張大你的嘴.
Open your mouth wide.
行了，孩子. 全部完工.
That's it, son. All done.
你是個真正的英雄！
You're a real hero!
你做到了...
You did it...
沒有啜泣.
without a whimper!
沒有顫抖.
Without trembling!
沒有落淚.
Without a tear!
你是佐杜洛夫斯基的一員！
You are a Jodorowsky!
來吧.
Come here!
怎麼了突然？
Now what?
別像個女孩一樣！
Don't be such a girl!
你是我兒子！站起來混蛋！
You're my son!
Stand up, damn it!
我絆倒了，爸爸，我沒事.
I tripped, Papa, I'm fine.
這才是我的孩子.
That's my boy.
意志能夠克服一切.
Willpower overcomes all.
再見，胡里奧先生，謝謝你.
See you, Don Julio. Thank you.
我會帶酒給你來的.
I'll send you the bottles.
-要法國紅酒，傑先生.
-好.
- Make it French wine, Don Jaime.
- Of course.
冰淇淋，冰淇淋，冰淇淋.
Ice cream!
地，水，火，風四種口味.
Water, air, earth and fire flavours!
你非常努力，兒子.
You made a great effort, my son.
嗯，爸爸.
Yes, Papa.
你該去呼吸一下海風.
You need to breathe some sea air.
會舒服許多.
You'll feel better.
嗯，爸爸.
Yes, Papa.
我必須回店里了.
I have to get back to the shop.
待在這兒看看大海吧.
Stay here and look at the sea.
嘿，孩子！
Hey, boy!
你勇敢嗎？
Are you brave?
當然！
Yes, I am!
那你等在那兒.
Then wait there.
怕了嗎？
Are you scared?
才沒有，聖徒.
No, Theosophist.
-為什麼不怕？
-我是個男人，聖徒.
- Why not?
- I'm a man, Theosophist.
-你知道我？
-是的.
- You know my name?
- Yes.
-誰告訴了你我的事？
-我爸爸.
- Who told it to you?
- My papa.
哈哈哈你爸爸.
Your papa!
來，我教導你如何冥想.
Look, I'll show you how to meditate.
跟著我念：
Say after me:
揭諦
Gate.
波羅揭諦
Paragate.
波羅僧揭諦
Parasamgate.
菩提娑婆訶.
Bodhi Svaha.
揭諦，於知識之中.
Gate, in the intellect.
揭諦，於內心之中.
Gate, in the heart.
揭諦，於性別之中.
Gate, in the sex.
波羅揭諦，還要更深入.
Paragate, even deeper.
波羅僧揭諦，心靈.
Parasamgate, heart.
菩提娑婆訶，極樂！
Bodhi Svaha, happiness!
Bodhi Svaha, happiness,
極樂，極樂，極樂，
happiness, happiness, happiness,
極樂，極樂！
happiness, happiness!
跟我一起.
Come with me.
揭諦揭諦，波羅揭諦，波羅僧揭諦，菩提娑婆訶.
Gate, Gate, Paragate, Parasamgate, Bodhi Svaha.
你知道這些纜車存在於此地多久了嗎？
Do you know how long
these cable cars have been here?
我不清楚，聖徒.
I don't know, Theosophist.
千萬年億萬年
Thousands and thousands
甚至億億年.
and thousands of years.
你根本無從得知它們來自何處去向何處，
You don't know where they come from
nor where they go,
但你可以帶走一塊它們的岩石，
but you can take one of their rocks
并如同寶物一般珍藏它/
and keep it like a treasure.
來.
Come.
這些渡船就像我們的肉體，載著我們的靈魂.
Those oars are like our bodies
which carry our souls.
靈魂是一件珍寶，
The soul is a treasure,
神就在我們體內.
the god within us.
我要給你一件禮物.
I'm going to give you a present.
看到這三個勛章了嗎？
See these three medals?
它們認為彼此是不同的，分裂的.
They think they're separate.
將它們投入熔爐，
Melt them down in an oven,
就會化為單一的液滴.
and they will turn into a single drop.
來，收下它們.
Here, have them.
用它們做一串項鏈，
Make a necklace with them
時刻佩戴它們以此提醒自己，
and wear it all the time to remind you
單純的神能夠統一這三者.
that a single god unites the three of them.
謝謝你，聖徒.
Thank you, Theosophist.
我愛這個香味.
I love this perfume.
把飲料放下.
Put that drink down.
我喜歡它.
I feel like it.
我不喜歡.
I don't feel like it.
我喜歡！
Well, I do!
這裡誰說了算？
Who commands here?
你.
You.
過來！
Come!
你是我的！
You are mine!
看我得到了什麼.
Look what I've got.
冷靜點，孩子.
Calm down, boy.
-快看！
-這是什麼？
- Look!
- What is it?
勛章！
Medals!
-誰給你的？
-聖徒.
- Who gave them to you?
- The Theosophist.
我告訴過你不准去見他！
I told you not to see him!
把這些垃圾給我.
Show me this rubbish.
瘋狂的白癡！
Crazy idiot!
用虛無的夢麻痺自己對死亡的恐懼！
Numbing his fear of death
with idle dreams!
跪下.
On your knees!
神不存在.
God does not exist!
人只有死亡隨後腐爛！
You die and you rot!
不存在超越於此的事物！
There's nothing beyond!
你的父親永遠不欺騙你！
Your father never lies!
你相信誰，我還是那個白癡？
Who do you believe, me or that idiot?
我該如何選擇？
Who was I going to choose?
我相信你，爸爸，那個乞丐瘋了.
I believe you, Papa. The beggar is crazy!
神並不存在，人只有死亡隨後腐爛.
God does not exist. You die and you rot.
不存在超越於此的事物.
There's nothing beyond.
非常好！你可以站起來了.
Bravo! Up you get.
勇士會戰勝自己編織的謊言.
A warrior overcomes his delusions.
現在快去睡覺.
Now go to bed!
每週三，
Every Wednesday,
深夜時分，
late at night,
我都會被父親離開家的聲音驚醒，
I awoke and looked on anxiously
一臉焦慮.
as my father left the house.
他去了哪裡？
Where was he going?
喜歡什麼樣的？
Do you fancy some?
來吹一個吧，傑？
Blowjob, Jaime?
居然在思考永恆的生命.
Think of the life eternal.
來玩樂透！來贏一隻雛雞！
Lotto! Win a chick!
來啊，蘿莉塔.
Come, Rosita.
這是屬於我們的托科皮亞.
This is our Tocopilla.
我們要為它奉獻些什麼.
We have to do something for it.
我有一場重要的秘密會議.
I have an important secret meeting.
改天再見，好麼？
Another time, alright?
傑，你知道我喜歡你，
Jaime, you know I like you
我也從不試圖改變你.
and I've never charged you.
安好啊，同志們.
Greetings, comrades!
安好，同志.
Greetings, comrade!
壞消息，同志們，我們有危險了.
Bad news, comrades. We're in danger.
伊瓦涅斯正在領導一場法西斯專政.
Ibáñez is heading for a fascist dictatorship.
宰殺工人和學生已經滿足不了他了.
Slaughtering workers
and students wasn't enough.
跟隨那些美國銀行家投機也不行.
Nor speculating with Yankee bankers.
如今，他想要囚禁所有的共產主義者.
Now, he wants to intern all the communists.
聽著，同志們
Listen, comrades!
我的夥伴安布羅希亞寄給我一封信.
My friend Ambrosia
has sent me a letter.
信？
A letter?
“親愛的托納，我有些可怕的消息要告訴你.”
"Dear Toña,
I have something dreadful to tell you.
“按伊瓦涅斯命令，
"On Ibáñez's orders, the police
警察正在搜捕同性戀并實施溺刑.
"are drowning the homosexuals.
我的情人，一位將我視作女性的同性戀警察，
"My lover, a queer cop
who pretends I'm a woman,
用沉重的鐵鏈捆綁了十名同好，
"tied ten of them to a heavy chain,
押上飛機將他們拋入大海.
"put them on a plane
and threw them in the sea.
你和姐妹們的生命都受到了威脅.
"You and our sisters live under threat.
小心行事，愛你的，安布羅希亞.”
"Take care.
Love, Ambrosia."
先是共產主義者，
First the communists,
然後是同性戀，
then the homosexuals,
再之後是學生，罷工的水手，礦工...
then the students,
the sailors on strike, the miners...
我們要忍耐多久？
How long are we going to stand this?
多久！？
Yes, how long?
我們可以組織一場大罷工，
We could organise a general strike
通過傳單，郵件，
by means of leaflets, letters
和秘密集會.
and secret meetings.
我們如何啟動這一切？
How would we fund all that?
我們甚至沒錢購買一杯飲料.
We don't even have enough to buy a drink.
-托納同志.
-怎麼了，傑.
- Comrade Toña?
- Yes, Jaime.
買些啤酒來吧.
Bring us some beers.
好樣的，佐杜洛夫斯基同志！
Bravo, Comrade Jodorowsky!
不准稱呼我佐杜洛夫斯基！
Don't you Jodorowsky me!
同志們，你們知道的，
Comrades, you know full well
我真正的名字只有一個，
my real name is the one
印在我的共產主義證件上：
on my communist card:
胡安·阿勞卡尼亞.
Juan Araucano.
抱歉，胡安同志.
Sorry, Comrade Juan.
現在起，我們必須像宦官一樣度日，
From now on,
we must live as eunuchs,
撕碎所有證據，
destroy compromising documents
閉緊自己的嘴巴，直到好日子來臨.
and keep our mouths shut
until we see better days.
說到就要做到.
No sooner said than done!
就這麼幹吧.
So be it.
-別這麼大驚小怪
-閉嘴，你這婊子.
- Stop that fuss!
- Shut up, you bitch!
-你才是婊子！
-喂，別這樣.
- You're a bigger bitch than I am!
- Come on! Stop that!
我們應該做些什麼，姑娘們，不能就這麼算了.
We've got to do something, girls!
We can't go on like this.
同志們！
Comrades!
乾杯！
Cheers!
全世界的工人們...
Workers of the world...
團結起來！
Unite!
起來，饑寒交迫的奴隸，
Arise ye workers from your slumbers
起來，全世界受苦的人.
Arise ye prisoners of want
乾杯吧，同志們！
Cheers, comrades!
乾杯！
Cheers!
共產黨萬歲！
Long live the Communist Party!
烏克蘭小屋正在販售紅鼻頭，
The Casa Ukrania offers you a red nose
現在購買九折優惠...
and 10% off all purchases...
閉嘴！
Shut up!
把那鼻頭摘下來.
Take off that nose!
-我有個驚喜要給你.
-是什麼，爸爸？
- I've got a surprise for you.
- What, Papa?
稍後你就知道.
You'll see.
立正！
Attention!
稍息.
At ease!
卡讚同志，我們永遠不會忘記你.
Comrade Kazan, we will never forget you.
我們永遠不會忘記你！
We will never forget you!
我們的吉祥物去世了，
Our mascot has passed away
就在距離我們一年一度的遊行前三天，
just three days before our annual parade,
不過，我們找到了人來代替他.
but we have found someone to replace him.
我榮幸地通知你，大家一致讚成，
I am proud to inform you that everyone agrees.
你，就是托科皮亞消防隊的新任吉祥物.
You are the new mascot
of Tocopilla's Fire Brigade!
我不想當吉祥物，我又不是狗.
I don't want to be a mascot. I'm not a dog.
這是榮譽，年輕的同志.
It is an honour, little comrade.
別的孩子都會嫉妒你.
The other children will envy you.
-他們會嘲笑我.
-那也是源於嫉妒.
- They'll laugh at me!
- Out of envy!
閉嘴！
Shut up!
來，穿上它.
Here, put it on.
你會像個英雄.
You'll look a hero.
不要！
No!
除非你給我那個黑人穿的鞋子.
I will if you give me
the black man's shoes.
什麼黑人？哪一雙鞋？
What black man? What shoes?
那雙商店櫥窗里人偶穿著的紅鞋.
The red shoes of the dummy in the window.
那個人偶非常昂貴.
That automaton was very expensive.
它一定要裝扮高雅.
It has to be elegant.
要是赤著腳，人們會怎樣議論它？
What will people say
if it's barefoot?
給它穿我的鞋子不就好了.
Put him in my shoes.
-這雙鞋多醜陋！
-是你買的！
- They're ugly!
- You bought them!
我從來不買醜陋的東西.
I don't buy ugly things.
怎麼樣？
Well then?
好吧，你說服了我.
Alright then. You've persuaded me.
你可以擁有它們.
You can have them.
謝謝您.
Thank you.
卡利托斯！
Carlitos!
看，我得到一雙新鞋！
Look, I've got new shoes!
我從來沒見過這麼漂亮的鞋子.
They're the most beautiful shoes
I've ever seen.
沒錯！
That's right.
你怎麼哭了？
Why are you crying?
我永遠無法擁有這樣一雙鞋.
I'll never have shoes like those.
來，穿上它們吧.
Here, have them.
-給我？
-是的.
- For me?
- Yes.
卡利托斯！
Carlitos!
-這是什麼？
-卡利托斯的工具箱
- What's this?
- Carlitos' box.
你的鞋呢？
Where are your shoes?
我把它們給了他.
I gave them to him.
你是不是瘋了？
Are you mad or what?
我為他感到難過，他太窮了！
I felt sorry for him. He's poor!
去把它們要回來.
Go and get them back.
不行，他跑去海邊了.
I can't. He went to the beach.
那個小鬼會來取他的工具箱的.
That brat will be back
to fetch his box.
去廣場等他，把鞋要回來，
Go to the square,
wait for him
他敢不給你就揍他一頓！
and get them, even if you have to punch him!
好的，爸爸.
Yes, Papa.
這孩子怎麼了，教授？
What happened to the boy,
professor?
他在礁石上玩耍，
He went to play on the rocks.
膠底鞋使他滑倒了.
The rubber soles made him slip.
他跌入了大海，這個蠢孩子就這麼淹死了.
He fell into the sea.
And the silly boy drowned.
就這樣，我童年的玩伴，化作了海灘的標誌，
And so our school friend
became a seaside icon,
永遠被囚禁在這座庇護所之中，
imprisoned forever
in that sanctuary,
供人祭奠、祈福.
devoted to the granting
of miracles.
去吧.
Go on!
苦難，救濟，
Suffering, relief,
救濟，苦難...
relief, suffering...
這鏈條永遠不會終結.
the chain is never-ending.
你們有一個小時自由玩耍！
You can play for an hour!
嘿，匹諾曹.
Hey, Pinocchio!
-想跟我們一起玩兒嗎？
-在哪裡？
- Do you want to come with us?
- Where?
那邊的岩石之間.
Among the rocks.
-我們準備打主教.
-打什麼？
- We're going to beat the bishop.
- Beat the what?
來了你就懂了.
Come and find out.
來啊，匹諾曹，來打倒他！你會喜歡的！
Come on, Pinocchio, beat off!
You'll enjoy it!
他那根和別人不一樣，哈哈哈！
His prick is different!
我們都是香蕉，他是根蘑菇，哈哈哈！
We've got a banana,
he's got a mushroom.
他沒有包皮，他的尖端是鈍的，哈哈哈.
He has no foreskin,
his end is blunt.
你不合群，匹諾曹，走開吧.
Your difference bothers us! Go away!
醜陋的猶太人.
Ugly Jew!
停步.
Stop!
別跳下去.
Don't jump!
你不是孤獨的，有我陪著你.
You are not alone.
You are with me.
所有你將要成為的，你已經成為了.
All you are going to be,
you are already.
所有你竭力尋求的，你已經得到了.
What you are looking for
is already within you.
擁抱你的苦難吧，
Embrace your sufferings,
因為通過它們，你將來到我的身邊.
for through them
you will reach me.
二十年后，我又會成為誰呢？
And who shall I be
in twenty years?
一百年後，千萬年后呢？
In a hundred?
In tens of thousands?
那時我的意識是否仍然需要一個肉體？
Will my consciousness
still need a body?
對你而言，我尚不存在.
For you,
I do not yet exist.
對我而言，你也已成泡影.
For me,
you do not exist anymore.
在時間的盡頭，
At the end of time,
當所有的物質，回歸到了原點，
when all matter returns
to its origin,
你和我，僅僅成為一段記憶，
you and I
will have just been memories,
沒有什麼是眞實的.
nothing real.
某個東西在夢著我們.
Something is dreaming us.
擁抱這幻覺吧.
Embrace the illusion.
活下去.
Live!
烏克蘭小屋！烏克蘭小屋！高價在我們這裡不值一提！
Casa Ukrania!
We swallow high prices!
傑！
Jaime!
亞歷桑德羅！
Alejandrito!
下去，你這蠢貨！
Get down, you fool!
我是消防隊的一員，我也想參與滅火.
I'm a fireman!
I'm here to put out the fire.
-佩德拉薩，關掉引擎！
-不行.
- Pedraza, stop the engine!
- I can't!
貧民窟火勢正旺.
The slums are burning.
我們必須趕快，否則傷亡慘重！
We must hurry
or they'll be dead!
可惡！抓緊了，你這白癡！
Damn it!
Hold tight, you idiot!
拿好這個哨子.
Take this whistle.
這里的遊民都是竊賊.
These dossers are thieves.
他們膽敢靠近，
As soon as they get too close,
你就吹響哨子，我會來趕走他們.
blow your whistle
and I'll kick them up the ass.
懂了嗎？警覺！
Got it? Attention!
知道了，爸爸.
Got it, Papa.
走遠點！
Clear off!
婊子養的！
Son of a bitch!
滾開！
Fuck off!
這個，我沒有失職.
Here. I didn't let them steal it.
你在期許稱讚嗎？
You're looking for compliments?
你只是盡責而已.
You only did your duty.
立定！
Halt!
佩德拉薩長官哪兒去了！？
Captain Pedraza is missing!
他還在那邊！
He's still over there!
在這兒！
Here he is!
你看.
Look.
看！
Look!
立定！
Halt!
神并不存在.
God does not exist.
你會死去然後腐爛.
You die and you rot.
不存在超越於此的事物！
There's nothing beyond!
我死了，爸爸.
I'm dead, Papa!
冷靜，你這寄生蟲.
Calm down, you louse!
別讓我難堪.
Don't embarrass me.
你是我們的吉祥物！
You're the mascot!
沒事.
It's nothing.
他很好.
He'll be fine.
他只是有點發熱.
He woke up with a temperature.
我會送他回家，隨後就歸隊.
I'll take him home and come back.
繼續進行！
Carry on!
你沒叫醒我，已經這麼晚了.
You didn't wake me up!
It's late.
我上學遲到了.
I've missed school.
你在葬禮上昏倒了.
You fainted at the funeral.
醫生說你需要休息.
The doctor said to let you rest.
你睡了整整兩天.
You slept solidly for two days.
感覺好些了嗎？
Do you feel better now?
是的，爸爸，我挺好的.
Yes, Papa, I feel really well.
是麼，我感覺很糟.
Well, I feel really bad.
你表現得像個懦夫.
You acted like a coward.
現在，他們都在恥笑我.
Now they're laughing at me.
如果兒子是懦夫，那父親肯定也一樣.
If the son is a coward,
the father must be too.
就算身穿消防員的裝束，猶太人不過是猶太人.
Even dressed up as a fireman,
a Jew is a Jew.
-我很抱歉，爸爸.
-閉嘴！
- I'm very sorry, Papa.
- Shut up!
看著它.
Look!
市長先生，他們來了.
Mr Mayor, they're coming!
-多少人？
-三百人.
- How many?
- 300.
什麼？
What?
快點，奎瓦斯，
Hurry, Cuevas,
拉響警笛！
give the alarm!
停下腳步！
Now stay here!
膽敢往前一公分，
If you dare move an inch,
我們就射穿你！
we'll shoot you!
你們對托科皮亞是一個威脅.
You pose a threat to all of Tocopilla.
你們攜帶著鼠疫！
You're carrying the plague!
有水嗎？哪裡能喝到水？
What about water? Where's the water?
問神去要吧！
Ask God for it!
給我們水，該死的！
Water, damn it!
水！
Water!
我們要水！
We want water!
水！
Water!
肅靜！
Silence!
若不保持肅靜，
If you don't keep quiet,
就把你們全部射死！
you'll all be shot!
全部！
All of you!
等等，傑！
Wait, Jaime!
這太瘋狂了！不要去！
It's crazy! Don't go!
安靜點，女人！
Silence, woman!
我會讓那群該死的消防員看看，
I will show those fucking firemen
到底誰更勇敢！
I'm braver than them.
水！
Water!
鎮靜，所有人都有份！
Calm down,
there's enough for everyone!
我的驢子！
My donkeys!
不！
No!
你們在吃我的驢子！
You're eating my donkeys!
我明天要如何再送水來？
How will I bring the water tomorrow?
明天？我們今天還沒吃飽！
Tomorrow? We're hungry today!
傑！
Jaime!
爸爸！
Papa!
他們會來燒了我！
They're going to burn me!
爸爸！
Papa!
不會的！
Never!
他們永遠別想燒了你！
They will never burn you!
夠了，別把你自己鎖在裡面！
That's enough,
don't shut yourself in!
如果你不屈服，你們全家都要受死.
If you don't surrender,
you will all die.
你的商店，會成為傳染源！
Your shop will be
a source of infection!
我親愛的兒子，
My dear son,
你絕不能被感染.
you mustn't get infected.
去吧，去洗凈你的雙手，
Go and wash your hands
躲在浴室中吧.
and lock yourself in the bathroom.
好吧，媽媽.
Yes, Mama!
神啊，
God,
我感覺得到你就在我體內.
I feel You inside of me.
我是你的一部分.
I am a part of You.
我不值一提，
I am nothing,
我愚昧無知，
I know nothing,
我渺小無力.
I can do nothing.
你是萬事萬物，
You are everything,
你洞悉一切，
You know everything,
你全知全能！
You can do everything!
我是淺灘，
I am the bank
而你，
of the vast river
是廣闊的河川.
that You are.
從我身上奔湧而過，
Break through me
以你那治愈的洪濤中
and let the waters
湧動的水流
of Your healing flood
沖洗他吧！
wash over him.
傑.
Jaime.
這是個奇跡！
It's a miracle!
噢，不，不，我救不了人們.
No, no!
I couldn't save the people.
這裡沒有我的根.
I have no roots.
這裡不是我的祖國.
This is not my country.
我輸了.
I failed.
你不能輸.
You cannot fail.
你同斯大林一樣強大.
You are as strong as Stalin.
不！
No!
是的，你是.
Yes, you are.
甚至更強.
Even stronger.
你同神一樣強大.
You are as strong as God.
神不存在！
God does not exist!
他存在.
Yes He does.
是他治愈了你.
He cured you.
在你心中
Feel His presence
感知此時此地的他吧.
in your heart.
在我的心中，只有你.
In my heart,
there is only you.
薩若，
Sara,
薩若，薩若，
Sara, Sara,
我的薩若，
my Sara,
我摯愛的薩若，
my devoted Sara,
我飽受苦難的薩若，請原諒我.
my long-suffering Sara,
forgive me.
你喚回了我的力量.
You have restored my strength.
如今我知道該怎樣拯救所有窮人了！
Now I know how to save all the poor!
智利不能永遠被暴君編織的謊言蒙蔽.
Chile cannot put up
with a tyrant's lies forever.
我要前往聖地亞哥，
I'll go to Santiago
為他的腦袋放入一枚子彈！
and put a bullet through his head!
玩兒夠了吧！我們沒時間奉陪！
Enough now!
We won't wait any longer!
立刻出來，否則我燒了你的店鋪！
Come out right away,
or we'll burn your shop!
他們屈服了.
They're surrendering.
我們很健康，同志們.
We are alive, comrades.
-伊瓦涅斯去死吧！
-去死！
- Death to Ibáñez!
- Death!
看看這個，同志！
Here it is, comrades!
哈利路亞，我找到了！
Hallelujah, I found it!
-不，是我找的！
-閉嘴，同志.
- No, I did!
- Shut up, comrade.
-閉嘴，同志！
Shut up, comrade!
我不閉.
I won't shut up.
利己主義者！
Individualist!
算了.
I'll shut up.
睡吧，
Go to sleep,
我的甜心.
my little sweetheart.
薩若.
Sara!
看！
Look!
我找到他的弱點了.
I found his weak spot.
他愛自己養的馬勝過了一切！
He loves his horse more than anything else！
沒人會搜我這裡.
No bloody soldier will search me here.
傑，你瘋了！
Jaime, you're mad!
如果我失敗了，
If I fail,
我們也許再也見不到彼此.
we may never see one another again.
我活著一日，
As long as I live,
就愛你一日.
I will love you.
只要我存在於世，
As long as I live,
就愛你永遠.
I will love you.
但這愛多麼孤單,
But this love so lonely
蘊我胸口,
in my breast
它將找到一個庇護所，
will find sanctuary
成為屬於我自己的
and be a secret
一個秘密.
of my own.
成為屬於我自己的
And be a secret
一個秘密.
of my own.
只要我活著一日，
As long as I live,
就愛你一日.
I will love you.
媽媽！
Mama!
原諒我.
Forgive me!
起來，饑寒交迫的奴隸，
Arise ye workers from your slumbers
你想殺掉伊瓦涅斯.
You want to kill Ibáñez.
是秘密警察嗎？
Are you the secret police?
-你要逮捕我嗎？
-並非如此.
- Are you arresting me?
- It's not that.
我不會讓你得逞因為這件事必須我來做！
I won't let you kill him
because I have to do it!
三個理由：第一，你是個猶太佬，
For three reasons: One, you are a Jew
必須由智利人處決他.
and a Chilean must kill him.
第二，
Two,
你老了而我很年輕.
you are old and I am young.
第三，那個處決他的人，將留名青史.
Three, he who kills him will go down in history.
而那一定會是我！
And that has to be me!
放手！
Let go!
你這白癡！
You idiot!
-哪裡來的槍？
-是我父親的，
- Where did you get this gun?
- It was my father's,
一名批判伊瓦涅斯的記者.
a journalist who criticised Ibáñez.
他們逮捕并殺害了他.
They arrested and killed him.
我明白.
Now I understand.
你並非想留名青史，你想替父親報仇.
You don't want to go down in history,
you want to avenge your father.
為除掉他我願奉獻我的生命.
I'll give my life to get rid of him.
好吧.
Alright.
這樣，
Look,
毀了他的世界吧，你來，
you rid the world of him
我協助.
and I'll help you.
行吧，同志.
Alright, comrade.
女士們先生們，心愛小狗的主人們，
Ladies and gentlemen,
owners of these beloved dogs,
現在是頒獎時間.
the time has come to award our two prizes.
第一個獎項，
First prize,
金骨頭，
the Golden Bone,
得主是，蝴蝶犬.
goes to the butterfly-dog.
這邊，請.
This way, please.
銀骨頭，
And the Lead Bone,
頒給最蠢著裝，
for the worst costume,
得主是...
goes...
袋鼠犬.
to the kangaroo-dog.
肅靜！奏樂！奏國歌！
Silence! Music!
The national anthem!
別開槍！
Don't shoot!
他不至於得到這樣一種死！
He doesn't deserve
such a death!
死就是死.
Death is death!
我不想生活在一個有著喬裝打扮的狗的世界.
I don't want to live in a world
of dressed up dogs.
它讓我惡心.
It makes me sick.
異教徒！你毀了我的基督！
Heretics!
You destroyed my Christ!
立定！
Halt!
別瞄準這個男人.
Don't shoot this man!
把這個可憐人送去公墓,
Take this poor man
to the communal grave,
和他的袋鼠犬一起.
together with his kangaroo-dog.
演出必須繼續進行！
The show must go on!
為了救總統，
To save the President,
這個男人冒著生命的危險！
this man risked his life!
如果槍點火了，你現在已成死尸.
If the gun had fired,
you would be dead now.
你應當得到回報.
You deserve a reward.
我不是要錢，先生，
I'm not asking for money, sir,
這只是我的善意.
just a favour.
我很愛馬，
As I love horses,
我夢想能成為你的馬夫.
my dream would be to become your groom.
你的請求適時.
Your request is timely.
阿基里斯先生，我的老馬夫，
Don Aquiles,
my old groom,
想要退休了.
wants to retire.
我會送你去我的宅子，那裡他可以訓練你.
I'll send you to my estate so he can train you.
一到兩個月時間，我們到時看看你進展如何.
In a month or two, I'll see how you're getting on.
阿基里斯為您效勞，先生.
Aquiles, at your service, sir.
不必太過恭敬，阿基里斯先生.
No need to be so respectful,
Don Aquiles.
我僅僅是你的學生.
I am merely your pupil.
跟我來.
Come along with me.
這塊地上唯一的建築，
The only buildings on the land
就是這些皇家馬廄，
are these right royal stables,
只為布塞弗勒斯而造，我的國王.
made just for Bucephalus, my king.
我來向你介紹我的美人.
I'll introduce you
to my handsome.
但要千萬小心，他不太信任人.
But be right careful,
he don't trust nobody.
你睡這裡,
You'll be sleeping here,
就在我旁邊.
right next to me.
我們要在每天破曉時分準時起床，
For we'll be up
at the crack of dawn every day
來檢查布塞弗勒斯的健康和情緒.
to see to Bucephalus'
health and comfort.
跑吧.
Walk!
跟他聊聊.
Talk to him now.
你的聲音必須直抵它的耳蝸，進入它的心靈.
Your voice must go right in his ear
to reach his heart.
-布塞弗勒斯.
-那聲音來自你的腦殼.
- Bucephalus.
- That voice is from your head!
認真點兒，夥計！
C'mon, man!
試著理解.
Try to understand that.
它應當發自你胸口，
It's got to be from your chest.
由內心深處.
Right from the heart.
布塞弗勒斯...
Bucephalus...
你擁有一切.
you have everything.
我在街頭長大，
I grew up on the streets,
飽受蔑視，
treated with contempt,
遊走于殘酷的人群中，
amongst cruel people,
像狗一樣咆哮，
howling like a dog
只為了一點感情.
for a bit of affection.
他們把我鎖進了一個堡壘.
They shut me up in a fortress.
現在我成了這樣，
And there I remain,
對感情感到飢餓.
hungry for affection.
沒人給過我現在你給我的感覺.
No one has given me
what you give me now.
非常好，傑！
Well done, Jaime!
你就要贏得布塞弗勒斯的芳心了.
You'll win over Bucephalus yet!
眞是非常好！
Really well done!
現在你可以帶他走走了.
Now you can take him for a walk.
怎麼了，先生？
Yes, sir?
我願為您效勞，卡洛斯閣下.
I'm at your service, Don Carlos.
布塞弗勒斯很不錯.
Bucephalus is right well.
是，先生.
Yes, sir.
是，他會被備好的.
Yes, he'll be saddled up.
怎麼了？
What is it?
上校隨時會要求
The colonel can ask at any time
來看望他的摯友.
after his best friend.
他明天就要來.
He's coming tomorrow.
對我來說，是時候該走了.
As for me, the time has come to leave.
什麼？
What?
你的墳鑿好了，阿基里斯先生.
Here is your grave,
Don Aquiles.
脫下你的衣服，
Take off your clothes
穿上我的.
and put on mine.
永遠別摘下這頂帽子，朋友.
Never take this hat off, friend.
那樣布塞弗勒斯就永遠不會知道我走了.
That way Bucephalus
will never know I've gone.
他肯定會像愛我般愛你.
For sure he'll love you
as much as me.
我要放下我的靈魂了，
I'm giving up my soul,
它想要回家，
it wants to return home.
它只是偶然經過，遇到我.
It was just passing through here
with me.
多往我身上蓋點土.
Throw plenty of earth on me.
保證我被完全掩埋.
Make sure I'm well covered.
明天，什麼都不要告訴總統.
Tomorrow, don't say anything
to the President.
他不會注意到我走了.
He won't even notice I left.
結果，當權者要考慮太多問題，
After all, the mighty
have too much on their minds
根本無法記住我這樣的老鬼.
to remember an old bloke like me.
謝謝你，傑，我的朋友.
Thank you, Jaime, my friend.
好啊，阿基里斯先生.
Hello, Don Aquiles.
-布塞弗勒斯還好嗎？
-他很好，先生.
- How is Bucephalus?
- Very well, sir.
可我不是阿基里斯.
But I am not Aquiles.
狗類大賽，先生...
The dog competition, sir...
啊，對了！我怎能把你忘了？
Ah, yes!
How could I forget you?
沒事了.
It's fine!
等在這兒.
Wait here.
布塞弗勒斯，
Bucephalus,
我親愛的.
my love.
你長得多英俊，我的王子.
You look so handsome, my prince.
讓我們看看你.
Let's have a look at you.
很好.
Good.
閃耀，閃耀，多麼美啊！
Splendid, splendid.
What a beauty!
恭喜你，阿基里斯先生，
Congratulations, Don Aquiles,
我的馬從未像現在看上去這麼優秀.
my horse has never
looked so well.
給你.
Here you are.
我不想要錢，先生.
I don't want money, sir.
-這都是愛的功勞.
-我欣賞你的態度.
- It's a labour of love.
- I like your attitude.
給你的供給加倍！
I'll double your supplies!
起身，阿基里斯，我們不是在教堂.
Get up, Aquiles!
We're not in church.
我準備先小跑一下，然後奔馳一小時.
I'm going to trot
then gallop for an hour.
我回來後，會把他交給你.
When I come back,
I'll leave the animal with you.
你要供他水和食物.
You will give him water and food.
我的馬是神聖的.
For my horse is sacred.
舞吧.
Dance!
啊，布塞弗勒斯！
Ah, Bucephalus!
他的罪行並非源於邪惡的靈魂，
His crimes are not the result of a wicked soul,
而是源於他磅礴的志氣.
but of an overwhelming generosity.
夠了！
Enough!
讓這些詭辯在我腦中消失！
Out of my head
treacherous thoughts!
他不是一個好父親，
He is not a good father,
他是頭惹人厭的豬，
he's a disgusting pig,
一頭嗜血的畜生，
a bloodthirsty brute,
一個癡癲的極端利己主義者！
a cretinous egomaniac!
他是個渾身屎臭的該死的軍人！
He's a damn soldier full of shit!
留心黃色的花朵.
Be careful with the yellow flowers!
馬兒們瘋狂地喜歡它.
These horses are wild about them.
而它卻是一劑致死的毒藥.
But it's a deadly poison.
你喜歡它們，是嗎？
You like them, don't you?
吃吧.
Eat.
主人，主人！
Master, master!
發生了什麼！？
What happened?
回答我，阿基里斯！
它怎麼了！？
Answer, Aquiles!
What happened to him?
神怎能允許這種事發生？
How can God allow this?
這麼高貴的一頭野獸！
Such a noble beast!
放鬆點，放鬆.
Easy now, easy.
我只是要給你打一針，
I'll just give you an injection
你會好起來的.
and you'll feel better.
乖孩子.
That's my boy.
該死的神，我要殺了你！
Damn God, I'm going to shoot you!
你馬上就會好起來.
You're going to feel better.
布塞弗勒斯！
Bucephalus!
求你不要死！
Please don't die!
不要！
Don't die!
謝謝你！
Thank you!
我們要把這裡燒掉.
We're going to burn it down.
全燒掉.
All of it!
你一直是一位忠實的僕人.
You have always been
a most loyal servant.
這次，收下這些錢吧.
This time, take the money.
全收下，
Keep it all
離開這裡吧.
and go away.
沒有了.
Nothing.
媽媽！
Mama!
怎麼了，亞歷桑德羅？
What's the matter,
Alejandrito?
在水泥鑄造的搖籃里，
Being in a cradle of cement,
被一片龐大的陰影繈褓著，
swaddled in a gigantic shadow,
束縛於自身虛無的存在.
bound to my empty existence.
困陷在這座肉體的島嶼上，
Trapped in this island of flesh,
通過記憶尋找自我，
searching for myself in memories,
什麼人也沒找到.
and meeting no one.
黑暗，正在吞噬一切.
The darkness
is swallowing everything.
它會毀滅我們.
It's going to devour us.
亞歷桑德羅，
Alejandrito,
我愛你對嗎？
do I love you?
是的，媽媽.
Yes, Mama.
有多愛？
How much?
像從天空到大地那樣寬廣.
From the sky to the earth.
這不是我的愛，
This is not my love,
這是來自神的愛，
it comes from God,
我僅僅是個信使.
I am merely the sender.
正是神創造了一切，
As God creates all,
所以我們都在傳播他的愛.
so we all radiate His love.
我的兒子，
My son,
黑暗其實像我一樣深愛著你，
the darkness loves you
as much as I do,
因為它是神的影子.
for it is God's shadow.
我真的很害怕.
I'm really scared.
它會消失的.
It's going to vanish.
黑色，
Black,
黑色，黑色.
black, black.
現在你和它一樣了，
Now you're just the same,
你屬於黑暗.
you belong to the darkness.
黑暗是你的王國，
Darkness is your kingdom
你是夜晚的怪物.
and you are a monster
of the night.
你非常飢餓.
You are hungry.
我很飢餓！
I am hungry!
你需要吞掉一位公主，來哺饗你的飢餓，
To feed your hunger
you need to devour a princess,
雪白無比的公主.
ever so white.
雪白無比！
Ever so white!
公主躲了起來.
The princess hides.
怪物要抓住她.
The monster has to catch her.
數到十！
Count up to ten!
一，
One,
二，三，四，五，
two, three, four, five,
六，七，八，九，十！
six, seven, eight, nine, ten!
我來了！
Here I come!
黑色.
Black.
我的母親溶入了黑暗.
My mother dissolved
into the darkness.
從此我再也不恐懼夜晚.
And never again
was I scared of the night.
卡利托斯？
Carlitos?
不可能！你是鬼魂嗎？
It can't be!
Are you a ghost?
你這白癡，我是他孿生兄弟盧喬.
You idiot,
I'm his twin Lucho!
-我很愛他.
-放開我！
- I loved him.
- Get off me!
是你殺了他.
You killed him.
從我視線中消失！我要工作了！
Out of my sight!
Let me work!
小盧喬！
Luchito!
安靜！
Quiet!
快看看誰在這兒！
Just look at what we have here!
是誰屈尊來探望我們？
Who deigns to visit us?
一個渾身肥皂臭的富家子弟！
A rich boy stinking of soap!
這個黑小子是我們的冠軍.
This dark one
is our champion.
讓我們看看這個蒼白的小子能不能保護自己！
Let's see if Paleface
can defend himself!
下注吧！
Place your bets!
富人還是窮人？
The rich or the poor?
窮人！
The poor one!
散開點兒！
Make a space!
出拳吧！誰先哭出來誰就輸了.
Let the punches fly!
The first who cries loses.
-他是我的朋友！
-我才不是，你這個蹩腳的猶太人.
- He's my friend!
- No, I'm not, you crappy Jew.
預備！
Get ready!
-一.
-一！
- One.
- One!
-二.
-二！
- Two.
- Two!
-三.
-三！
- Three.
- Three!
這不能算！他從後方偷襲！
That doesn't count! He came from behind!
不能算！
Yes!
安靜！
Quiet!
快來，他任你處置！痛毆這個叛徒！
Come on, he's all yours! Hit that traitor!
你怎么了？
What have you done?
沒事.我遇到了點意外.
Nothing. I was in La Urgencia.
他們笑我是猶太人，還打了我.
They called me a Jew
and hit me.
如果你想適應環境，
If you want to survive
你就要和光同塵.
you must go unnoticed.
我會將這些障礙從你腦子里去除.
I'm going to remove
these barriers from your mind.
丟掉匹諾曹！
Out with Pinocchio!
丟掉猶太人！
Out with the Jew!
丟掉鼻子和白皮膚！
Out with the nose
and white skin!
你完全空了！
You are empty!
你成為了不可見的！
You are invisible!
你確定沒人能看見我？
Are you sure I am invisible?
來.
Come!
我會脫光衣服，
I will get undressed
走進裡面去.
and go inside.
別，媽媽，這太危險了！
No, Mama, it's dangerous!
相信吧.
Have faith!
亞歷桑德羅.
Alejandrito!
我們就像空氣.
We are like air.
他們看不見我們，亞歷桑德羅，
They do not see us, Alejandrito,
更聽不見我們.
nor do they hear us.
空氣...
Air...
我們就是空氣.
We are air.
你教給爸爸如何隱形了嗎？
Did you teach my father to be invisible?
他不相信這些事.
He doesn't believe in such things.
所以死亡看得見他啊.
Then Death can see him.
也許它已經把他帶走了.
Maybe it has taken him away.
不，他沒死.
No, he's not dead.
如果他死了，
If he was
我心中一定會感知到.
my heart would tell me.
那他在哪裡？
Where is he?
這塊岩石
This stone
知道傑在哪裡.
knows where Jaime is.
你要傳達給他你的消息.
You are going to send him a message.
唾在上面.
Spit.
告訴他你想說的話語.
Now tell him
what it is you want to say.
別忘記我們，回來吧.
Don't forget us.
Come back.
停下！走遠點！
Stop it! Go away!
楚蔻，我漂亮的小狗.
Cuco, my pretty dog.
-怎麼了？
-女士，我的名字不叫楚蔻.
- What's the matter?
- Madam, my name isn't Cuco.
我叫傑·佐杜洛夫斯基！
I am Jaime Jodorowsky!
我為什麼在這裡？
What am I doing here?
這麼說你恢復了記憶.
So your memory has returned.
夢結束了.
The dream is over.
什麼？
What?
站起來.
Get up.
我發現你時你正流落街頭，
I found you wandering the streets,
飢腸轆轆.
half starved.
終於，殘酷的神派來了一位不討厭我的人.
Finally, cruel God sent someone
who wasn't repulsed by me.
我把你帶來和我一起生活.
I brought you to live with me.
我猜到總有一天你會記起你是誰，
Suspecting you would one day
be yourself again,
所以我給你寫了一封信.
I wrote you a letter.
沒人能逃離自己的命運.
No one escapes from their destiny.
我讀了它你就全明白了.
I'll read it so you understand.
“遇見你，就像找到一件珍寶.
"Meeting you was like finding treasure.
我就像一隻野狗，
"I was like a street dog,
在垃圾堆里翻到什麼吃什麼，
"eating what I could find
in the rubbish.
沒人給我一分錢.
"Nobody gave me a cent.
我在你手臂上塗了我們國旗的顏色，
"I painted your arms
the colours of our flag,
你癱瘓的手
"and your paralysed hands
成為了窮苦人民的標誌.
"became a symbol of the people's misery.
白天，你是我的寄託，
"In the day, you were my sustenance,
夜晚，你是我的榮光.
"and at night, my glory.
儘管你無法在床笫間
"Even though you couldn't caress me,
愛撫我，
"in bed on your back,
我也可以騎在你身上.
"I would mount you.
我知道你總有一天會醒來，
"Knowing you would wake up
one day,
我們的相聚讓我感到愉悅，
"I felt the joy of our union
也帶來了心知定會別離的痛苦.
"and the pain of knowing
it wouldn't last.
找回你的記憶，
"Recovering your memory,
你就從我生命中消失了，
"you disappear from my life
因此我的生命也消失了.”
"and therefore
my life disappears."
我的愛人，
My love,
願殘酷的神治愈你這雙手.
may cruel God heal these hands of yours.
它們是我渺小存在中的珠寶.
They have been the jewels
of my poor existence.
找回你的記憶，
Recovering your memory,
你就從我生命中消失了，
you disappear from my life
因此我的生命也消失了.
and therefore my life disappears.
殺人犯！
Murderer!
我需要幫助！
I need help!
罪人.
Sinner!
該死的牧師！
Damn priest!
我好餓，給我些食物！
I'm hungry!
Give me some!
給我，我好餓！
I'm hungry!
“聖木木工”
"SACRED WOOD CARPENTERS"
打擾，閣下...
Excuse me, sir...
這裡沒什麼“閣下”.
There's no "sir" here.
基督這個木匠都不傲慢，
If Christ the carpenter wasn't proud,
我又怎麼敢稱“閣下”？
then why should I be?
叫我約瑟就好了.
Just call me José.
打擾一下，約瑟...
Excuse me, José...
你需要什麼嗎？你看上去...
Do you need something?
You look
就像快進棺材似得.
as if you could do
with a coffin.
“倘若我忘了你，
"If I forget you,
哦，耶路撒冷，
"O Jerusalem,
情願我的右手忘記功能.”
"let my right hand
forget its skill!"
你都忘了嗎？
Have you forgotten so much?
你為什麼折磨自己？
Why are you punishing yourself?
聖潔的長老，
Saintly old man,
請僱我工作！
give me some work!
幫我磨這批椅子吧，我急於發貨.
Help me sand these chairs
I have to deliver urgently.
用心磨，我的兄弟.
Sand with your soul, my brother.
神的一切道路，都通向真實.
All God's paths lead to the truth.
約瑟，為什麼對我如此友善？
José, why are you so good to me?
“憂傷痛悔的心，
"A broken and contrite heart,
你必不輕看.”
"you will not despise."
詩篇第五十一.
Psalm 51.
那你不會輕視我？
But don't you despise me?
不會！
No!
在那海上，在那海上，
On the high sea!
有個遠航的水手，
There was a sailor sailing
他喜歡彈吉他，
He loved to play guitar
每當他思念，心愛的故鄉，
And when he remembered
his dear country
他就拿起吉他，高聲歌唱，
He'd take his guitar and he'd start to sing
在那海上，在那海上.
On the high sea!
我們做好了百十把椅子.
We've got the hundred chairs!
完工了.
The work is done.
這是我所以積蓄.
This is all I have.
-夠用嗎？
-當然夠！
- Will it be enough?
- Of course!
我準備搭火車去瓦爾帕萊索，
I'll take a train
to Valparaiso
在那裡乘船回托科皮亞.
then a boat to Tocopilla.
謝謝你！
Thank you!
歡迎光臨神之家！
Welcome to the House of God!
太棒了，你帶來了椅子.
Wonderful, you brought the chairs!
兄弟們，約瑟先生帶來了椅子.
Brothers,
Don José brought the chairs!
快過來！
Come quickly!
噢，主啊，我的上帝，
O Lord my God,
當我思及你的雙手，
When I, in awesome wonder,
創造的世界，
Consider all the worlds
我驚奇無比.
Thy hands have made
把你的重負都丟給主，
Cast your burden on the Lord,
他會替你承擔.
And He will sustain you.
他永遠不會遺棄
He shall never abandon
那些倒下的人.
he who falls.
歌唱吧！
Let us sing!
我的靈魂開始歌唱，
Then sings my soul,
神啊我的拯救者，為你而唱.
My Saviour God, to Thee
你是多麼偉大，
How great Thou art,
我的靈魂開始歌唱，
Then sings my soul
神啊我的拯救者，為你而唱.
My Saviour God, to Thee
你是多麼偉大，
How great Thou art,
可以了，兄弟們.
Enough, brothers!
現在讓我們跳躍二十六下，
Now let's jump 26 times
以感謝主的仁慈！
to thank our Lord for His mercy!
一！
One!
二！
Two!
三！
Three!
四！
Four!
五！六！
Five! Six!
七！
Seven!
八！
Eight!
九！
Nine!
十！
Ten!
十六！
Sixteen!
十七！
Seventeen!
十八！
Eighteen!
十九！
Nineteen!
二十！二十一！
Twenty! Twenty-one!
二十二！
Twenty-two!
二十三！
Twenty-three!
二十四！
Twenty-four!
二十五！
Twenty-five!
二十六！
Twenty-six!
哈利路亞！
Hallelujah!
兄弟們，
Brothers,
善良的約瑟死了.
the good José has died.
不！不！
No! No!
不是的，兄弟！
No, brother!
我們的兄弟死得多美.
What a beautiful death our brother had.
他的每一跳都引領他進入神的心房，
Each jump he gave brought him to the heart of God
在那裡他延續生命.
and there he remained.
為了每一把他免費獻給教堂的椅子，
For every free chair he offered to the church,
讓我們感謝神，
let us thank God,
他會為每個人準備一個天堂！
for he deserves a paradise
for each one!
讓我們站在這椅子上.
Let's climb on the chairs.
兄弟姐妹們！
Brothers and sisters!
大家可以為我們...
What do you think
of making a collection
兄弟的葬禮募捐嗎？
to pay for our brother's funeral?
好！
Yes!
誰能居住在你神聖的山岡？
Who may live on Your holy hill?
誰能於心中洞悉真理.
Who speaks the truth from his heart
就這些了.
That's all there is.
這樣，他就能被埋在公墓.
With this, he will end up
in the communal grave.
姐妹，
Sister,
幫我取出口袋里的東西，
take out what's in this pocket
交給牧師.
and give it to the Pastor.
放入帽子里吧.
Put it in the hat.
你這個傻瓜！你這個傻瓜！
You fool! You fool!
打倒國際猶太教組織！
Down with international Judaism!
敬禮！
Heil!
智利屬於智利人！
Chile for the Chileans!
智利人屬於納粹！
Chileans for Nazism!
納粹屬於智利！
Nazism for Chile!
納粹屬於伊瓦涅斯！
Nazism for Ibáñez!
立定！
Halt!
張開你的手掌，朋友！
Extend your hand, friend!
我不能，它萎縮了.
I can't. It's withered.
別胡扯！張開你的手，立刻！
Don't mock! Extend your hand now!
我說了我不行.
I'm telling you I can't do it.
該死的共產主義者！
Fucking communist!
張開你的手，混蛋！
Extend your hand, bastard!
我做不到.這雙手做不到！
I can't do it. Nor with this one!
他在嘲弄我們的敬意！
He is mocking our salute!
我們都是兄弟.
We're all brothers.
共產主義者的口號！
Communist propaganda!
打倒他！
Beat him up!
你這納粹白癡！
You stupid Nazi!
說：“祝福約瑟先生！”
Say: "Blessed be Don Jose!"
祝福約瑟先生.
Blessed be Don Jose!
繼續！
Again!
-祝福約瑟先生.
-繼續，否則我扯掉你的內臟！
- Blessed be Don Jose!
- Again, or I'll rip your guts out!
-祝福約瑟先生！
-你！
- Blessed be Don Jose!
- You!
祝福約瑟先生！
Blessed be Don Jose!
汪！汪！
Woof! Woof!
汪！
Woof!
祝福約瑟先生！
Blessed be Don Jose!
約瑟先生是是誰？
Who is Don José?
他是...
He's...
他是你的父親.
He's your father.
坦白吧.
Confess.
約瑟先生是誰？
Who is Don José?
他是你的兄弟.
He's your brother.
約瑟先生是誰？
Who is Don José?
他是你的兒子.
He's your son.
繼續！
Keep going!
約瑟先生是誰？
Who is Don José?
就是你.
You are.
我要把你的腦子崩出來！
I'm going to blow
your brains out!
約瑟先生是誰？
Who is Don José?
是你，是我，是我們.
You are, I am, we all are.
夠了！
Enough!
坦白！
Confess!
我愛你，約瑟先生！
I love you, Don José!
放鬆，
Easy!
放鬆，同志.
Easy, comrade!
我來了.
I'm here now.
看著我.
Look at me.
你自由了，同志.
You're free, comrade.
你自由了.
You're free.
獨裁結束了.
The dictatorship is over.
無法解決危機，伊瓦涅斯拋棄了權力.
Unable to solve the crisis,
Ibáñez has renounced power.
他逃去了阿根廷.
He fled to Argentina.
我想殺了他.
I wanted to kill him.
你是個英雄，同志.你飽受折磨.
You are a hero, comrade.
You resisted torture.
你成家了嗎？
Do you have a family?
是的.
Yes.
我家在托科皮亞.
My family is in Tocopilla.
我們能做的，只有帶你回故鄉了.
The least we can do
is take you back to your village.
走吧.
Let's go.
謝謝你.
Thank you.
當心點.
Be careful.
爸爸把我們都忘了.
Papa has forgotten us.
我怕他再也不會回來.
I'm scared he won't come back.
你是在害怕他不會回來？
Are you scared
he won't come back
還是在盼望他的歸來？
or don't you want him
to come back?
我希望只有我們兩個人，他根本不愛我.
I like it just the two of us.
He doesn't love me.
你錯了.
You're mistaken.
把耳朵湊過來.
Put your ear here.
靠在我胸口.
On my heart.
-聽到了嗎？
-是的.
- Can you hear it?
- Yes.
它告訴你什麼？
What is it telling you?
我的父親正在回家的路上.
My father is on his way home.
他很快就會到了！
He'll be here soon!
就這些？
Is that all?
不，它還說他會非常愛我.
No. It says he'll love me a lot too.
懂了嗎？
See?
當你感覺你的理智喪失了希望，
When you feel
your mind is losing hope,
聽從你的心靈吧.
always listen to your heart.
薩若！
Sara!
傑！
Jaime!
-是你.
-別碰我.
- It's you.
- Don't touch me.
不值得這麼做.
I don't deserve it!
我掌握了他.
I had him in my hands
但它們卻癱瘓了！
but they got paralysed!
我令你等待，
I made you wait,
我無謂地犧牲了你.
I sacrificed you needlessly.
我不值得你的愛.
I don't deserve your love.
我是個懦夫.
I'm a coward.
不，爸爸！你是最強大的.
No, Papa! You're the strongest.
男人永遠沒有恐懼.
Men are never scared.
我的兒子！
My Son!
你是我的靈魂.
You are my soul.
我會永遠
I will always
愛你.
love you.
算了吧，薩若.
Enough, Sara.
沒人能治愈我.
Nobody will be able to cure me.
你能夠治愈你自己.
You can cure yourself.
看看你的神！
Look at your god!
看看這些你欽佩的惡魔！
Look at the devil you admire!
不要！
No!
你在伊瓦涅斯身上找到了，
You found in Ibáñez
你在斯大林身上崇拜的一切.
all you admired in Stalin.
不要！
No!
而這就是你！
And here you are!
你和他們一樣！
You are the same as they are!
活在偽裝之下，
You have lived in the guise
偽裝成一個暴君.
of a tyrant.
我很抱歉.
I am so sorry.
這個在感受，在哭泣的男人，
This man who feels and cries,
這個人才是你.
this man is you.
我們愛你，愛現在這個，
We love you
as you are now,
更真實，
as, deep down,
永恆不變的你.
you have always been.
做回自己吧.
Be yourself again.
傑！
Jaime!
托科皮亞.
Tocopilla.
我由往昔扶搖遠去，
I soar away from the past,
停靠於此刻的軀殼中，
Land in the body present,
忍受著沉重而痛苦的歲月，
Bear the painful burden of years,
就在心中留下那個孩子吧，
Yet in the heart keep the child,
生命醞釀的果實，
As the bread of life,
像一隻白色的云雀，
As a white canary,
像一顆珍貴的寶石，
As a worthy diamond,
像是清澈無比，纖毫不立，
As a lucidity without walls,
沒有墻壁的阻隔，更沒有開敞的門窗，
Wide open doors and windows,
於是起了風，
Through which blows the wind,
只有風，
Only the wind,
風而已.
Just the wind.
烏克蘭小屋.
Casa Ukrania.
我們的價格，
Our prices
就是一個奇跡！
are a miracle!
為健康乾杯！
To your health!
無底船字幕組      傾情奉獻
翻譯   草心
本中文字幕由英文版本轉譯，交流探討請聯繫：ywang0310@gmail.com
再次重申，本字幕僅用於學習交流，希望大家支持正版
感謝觀看
後會有期
Adaptation: Christina Crevillén,
Michael Sheldon, Susannah Rooke
Subtitles: Eclair Group